Register of the Bertram David Wolfe papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1903-1977 (Boxes 54-151)
  - U.S.
    - Foreign relations
      - General
        - Lichtenstein, David S., "Some Notes on Hans Morgenthau, Robert W. Tucker and the New Isolationism,", undated; Typescript (Folder 143: 7)
      - Arab countries (Folder 143: 8)
      - China (Folder 143: 9-10)
      - Israel (Folder 143: 11)
      - Latin America (Folder 143: 12)
      - Russia
        - Clippings (Folder 144: 1-4)
        - Mimeographed material (Folder 144: 5)
        - Notes (Folder 144: 6-7)
        - Printed matter (Folder 145: 1-4)
        - Writings
          - Maddox, Robert James, "Cold War Revisionism and the Liberal Historians: The Reception of Revisionism by the Libera Community,", undated; Typescript (Folder 145: 5)
          - "An Open Letter to the American People,", undated; Typescript (Folder 145: 6)
      - Sweden (Folder 145: 7)
      - Vietnam (Folder 145: 8)
    - Historiography (Folder 145: 9-10)
    - Historiography (Folder 146: 1-2)
    - Information Agency (Folder 146: 3-4)
    - Politics and government (Folder 146: 5)
    - Popular culture (Folder 146: 6)
    - Race question
      - Clippings (Folder 146: 7-9)
      - Notes (Folder 147: 1)
      - Printed matter (Folder 147: 2)
    - Relations (general) with Russia
      - General (Folder 147: 3-4)
      - Hook, Sidney, "A Dialogue with an 'Unofficial' Soviet Russian Delegation,", undated; Typescript (Folder 147: 5)
    - Religion (Folder 147: 6-7)
    - Social conditions (Folder 147: 8)
  - University Centers for Rational Alternatives
    - General (Folder 147: 9-10)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Folder 147: 11)
  - Urbanization (Folder 147: 12)
  - Urena, Pedro Henriquez (Folder 147: 13)
  - Utopias (Folder 148: 1-2)
  - Viereck, Peter (Folder 148: 3)
  - Vietnam - History - Conflict (1961-1975)
    - General (Folder 148: 4-6)
    - Dan, Phan Quang, farewell statement, Washington D.C., 1968; Typescript (Folder 148: 7)
  - Violence
    - General (Folder 148: 8-9)
    - U.S. (Folder 149: 1-2)
  - Vishinskii, Andrei (Folder 149: 3)
  - Vlasov, Andrei - Schwarz, Solomon, "Tragediia Vlasovskogo Dvizheniia" (Tragedy of the Vlasov Division), undated; Typescript (Folder 149: 4)
  - Vol'skii, Nikolai
    - General (Folder 149: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1971 (Folder 149: 6)
  - War (Folder 149: 7-8)
  - Welfare economics - Logue, Dennis E. and Thomas D. Willett, "The Relation between the Rate and Variability of Inflation: Another Aspect of the Welfare Cost of Inflationary Finance,", 1975; Mimeograph (Folder 149: 9)
  - Williams, Duncan, Trousered Apes (Folder 149: 10)
  - Wilson, Edmund (Folder 149: 11)
  - Wit and humor, Eastern European (Folder 149: 12)
  - Wittfogel, Karl A.
    - General (Folder 149: 13)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1976 (Folder 149: 14)
  - Wolfe et al. v. Froehlke
    - Briefs, 1972-1974 (Folder 150: 1-2)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Folder 150: 3)
  - Workers Age (Folder 150: 4)
  - Workers School, New York City (Folder 150: 5)
  - World politics (Folder 150: 6-7)
  - World War (1939-1945)
    - General (Folder 150: 8)
    - Diplomatic history (Folder 150: 9-11)
    - Forced repatriation (Folder 150: 12)
    - Russia (Folder 151: 1)
  - Woytinsky, Wladimir (Folder 151: 2-3)
  - Zinov'ev, Grigorii
    - General (Folder 151: 4)
    - Hedlin, Myron W., "Consistency or Cowardice? Zinoviev in 1917,", 1972; Mimeograph (Folder 151: 5)
    - Hedlin, Myron W., "Grigorii Zinoviev: The Myths of the Defeated,", undated; Typescript (Folder 151: 6)
  - Zionism (Folder 151: 7)
- Card File (Boxes 152-153)
  Index card notes by Bertram D. Wolfe, mostly relating to Russian history, unsorted.
- Oversize File (Box 154)
  Oversize miscellany, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Krupskaia, Nadezhda (Folder 154: 1)
  - Leningrad maps (Folder 154: 2)
- Microfilm, 1917-1949 (Microfilm cabinet)
  Microfilm of writings by Bertram D. Wolfe and others, arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Chernov, Viktor, "TS.K.-P.S.R. na Rubezhe Dvukh Revoliutsii" (Central Committee of the Party of Socialist Revolutionaries on the Border between Two Revolutions), undated; Positive film of typescript (includes typewritten explanatory notes) (Reel 1)
  - Germany, Geheime Staatspolizei, Gestapo arrest list for England, undated; Negative film of printed copy (Reel 2)
  - "Kak Sovetuiut Reshit Vopros o Zemle Razlichnyia Politicheskiia Partii Rossii" (How the Different Political Parties of Russia Suggest Solving the Land Question), 1917; Positive film of printed copy (Reel 3)
  - Krupskaia, Nadezhda, "Instruktsiia o Peresmotre Knizhnogo Sostava Bibliotek k Iziatiiu Kontr-Revoliutsionnoi i Anti-Khudozhestvennoi Literaturi" (Instructions on Review of Library Books for Removal of Counter-Revolutionary and Anti-Art Literature), 1923; Negative film of printed copy (reel 4) and positive film (reel 5). (Reel 4-5)
  - Wolfe, Bertram D., Negative film of printed copies
    - "China's Fate," American Mercury, 1947 January (Reel 6)
    - "The Rise and Fall of the Comintern," American Mercury, 1947 March (Reel 6)
    - "Dissenting Opinion on Toynbee," American Mercury, 1947 June (Reel 6)
    - "Marx: The Man and His Legacy," American Mercury, 1947 September (Reel 6)
    - "Forced Labor in Soviet Russia," American Mercury, 1947 November (Reel 6)
    - "Stalin Worship in Russian Schools," American Mercury, 1948 January (Reel 6)
    - "The Individual vs. the State," American Mercury, 1948 March (Reel 6)
    - "Politics and Fiction in Mexico," American Mercury, 1948 June (Reel 6)
    - "What Next in China?," American Mercury, 1949 April (Reel 6)
    - "The Problem of Power," American Mercury, 1949 September (Reel 6)
- Sound Recordings, 1969-1979
  Sound recordings (sound cassettes and sound tape reels) of speeches by Bertram D. Wolfe and an oral history of Ella Wolfe, arranged chonologically.
  - Bertram Wolfe speech in the United States, undated; 1.0 sound cassette
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003420
    A talk on the Communist movement of which he was a part. Using a series of memories and stories, he concentrates on his history, how and why he became a communist, and his experiences in the Communist International.
  - "The Extraordinary Adventures of a Yankee in Mexico" speech, 1969 May 9
    - 2 sound tape reels
      Access
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003381
      Wolfe discusses his time in Mexico, starting with his assignment to teach English in the country through his deportation and return. He speaks at length about Diego Rivera. He touches on Leon Trotsky in the question-and-answer session.
      Different introduction than the recording on the sound cassettes and slightly more complete, but same program.
    - 2 sound cassettes
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003416
      Different introduction than the recording on the sound tape reels, but same program.
  - Bertram Wolfe addressing the University of Texas at Austin, "Reminiscences of the Communist International,", 1970 March 12; 1.0 sound tape reel
    Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003382
    Also includes "A Mexican Bandit in Communist Russia." Relates to the 5th Congress, Comintern, 1924. Introduced by Prof. Oliver Radkey.
  - "What Was Wrong with the American Revolution? A Study in Comparative Revolution," speech, American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies Convention, St. Louis, Missouri, 1976 October 8; 2.0 sound cassettes
    Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003417
    Wolfe discusses the American Revolution, in the process comparing it with the French and Russian revolutions. Figures he concentrates on are Benjamin Franklin, emphasizing his age; Thomas Jefferson, emphasizing his Virginian heritage as key to the revolution; John Adams, emphasizing his political skill; Thomas Paine, emphasizing reforms Paine wanted that Wolfe suggests would have led to totalitarianism; and George Washington, emphasizing his military background and understanding the value of retreat. Wolfe then talks about how important in-fighting is to the success or failure of a revolution. He finishes by noting all the founding fathers died in bed, save one that died in a duel.
  - Sound recording from the West Coast Association of Women Historians annual conference, a conversation with Ella Wolfe and Joan M. Todd and colleagues, 1979 April 21; 1.0 sound cassette
    Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003419
  - Professor Hugh Trevor-Roper speech at Colorado College, 1979 July 4; 1.0 sound cassette
    Use copy reference number: 77029_a_00003421
    A talk on Hitler's rise to power and the early days of the Third Reich. Trevor-Roper structures the talk as a recital of historical events, often commenting on the implication of these event. He also focuses on the Third Reich's relationships with communism and the Catholic Church. In English
  - Ella Wolfe oral history, 1982-1983
    1/4-inch sound tape reels and one sound cassette. Interview conducted by Ramon Myers, fellow at the Hoover Institution.
    - "Tape 1,", undated; 1.0 sound cassette
      Undescribed, undigitized.
    - 1982 October 18-22, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003348
      Topics: Growing up in Russia; life in New York; interlude in San Francisco; underground political meeting at St. Joe, Michigan; Mexico; and some recollections about Sidney Hook.
      The interview on 18 October 1982 begins with Wolfe describing growing up in Russia. She says that growing up, people around her often spoke about socialism. She then describes the town she grew up in and some examples of life in it. This leads to a discussion of Wolfe's education, which in turn leads to her elopement with Bertram. Wolfe claims that Bertram had never heard of socialism until he went to her house, where it was spoken about constantly.
      The conversation then moves to a discussion of the Wolfes' lives in America. First, Wolfe describes health problems. Describing their time in San Francisco, she notes that Bertram became involved in the Communist Party once in the city. She then describes how they got jobs to make a living, but quickly returns to stories about their involvement in the Communist Party. After tales about Bertram in the party, Myers asks about Jay Lovestone, to which Wolfe speaks about at length through various stories. In the process of describing the Party, the conversation moves to the Wolfes' work in Mexico. Included in this are stories about Diego Rivera. She says Frida Kahlo was one of the most extraordinary people she ever knew and a better painter than Rivera. While speaking about life in Mexico, she talks about Bertram's interaction with libraries and saving rare books. The recording ends with a discussion about Sidney Hook.
    - 1982 October 20-25, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003349
      Topics: Mexico, artists and people; Mexico, Bert and Soviet Embassy; recollections of Max Eastman; and New York, late 1920s and communist cell Friends (Whittaker Chambers, others).
      The discussion begins with stories about Bertram's book about strange communists, and the conversation briefly touches on happenings and conditions in Russia. However, most of the time is spent on the Wolfes' experiences in Mexico. Among the topics are Diego Rivera; Leon Felipe, describing him from a variety of angles, using stories to illustrate his character; a new library in Mexico; other communist painters and assassination attempts on Leon Trotsky; the relationship of the living with the dead; and the Soviet's view of Mexicans. Also, Wolfe describes Max Eastman.
    - circa 1982, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003351
      Topics: Trotskyite Movement, e.g. Europe and Mexico; Ella in Moscow, 1929; in New York and break with Communism; two individuals in Mexico, 1920s--Carlton Beales and Luis Alberto Sanchez, rector of St. Marcos.
    - 1982 November, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003352
      Topics: Forming the Moscow Communist International--Lu and Eva Geissler, M. N. Roy, Borodin, Lewis Frana (Corey) (wife Ester), Willi Münzenberg, (wife Elsa) Iqnaz Reis - Elsa Bernaut, G. Mandel (at Berkeley); Angelica Balabanov (Nov. 3, 1982); Victor Serge; Krivitsky; William Henry Chamberlin; Alexander Orloff; Bessedovsky and forgery in Paris; Bodgan-Raditsa and Bert Wolfe's letter to Bogdan; and Bogdan.
      Ella begins by talking about several people from the formation of the Communist International. She retells a variety of short stories about Lu and Eva Geissler; Lu's lover, M. N. Roy; Borodin selling diamonds in Central America to obtain funds for the Soviet Union; Lewis Frana; Willi Münzenberg and how he was killed for saying it was a tragedy communists fought other communists in the purges; Ignaz Reis; Elsa Bernaut; and G. Mandel from Berkeley, who at the time was still taking students to the Soviet Union and proclaiming it the promised land.
      The second conversation concerns Angelica Balabanov. Ella Wolfe considers her one of the best women she ever knew. She details how Balabanov became disillusioned with the communist revolution in Russia. Though Ella considers her a bit naive, she says she was completely devoted to her ideas. In the process, Ella discusses Victor Serge, Krivitsky, William Henry Chamberlin, Alexander Orloff, and briefly comments on the Hoover Institution and its collections.
      The third conversation concerns Bessedovsky and forgery in Paris and Bodgan-Raditsa and Bert Wolfe's letter to Bogdan.
    - 1982 November 12, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003353
      Topics: Ella comments about B. Wolfe; Ella and Bert's writing relationship; Ella and teaching Spanish literature; Ella's relationship with male professional-career types; comments on writers who worked for the New Leader, e.g., D. Bell; Judith Evans and J. Lovestone; Ella comments on the book Three Who Made a Revolution; memories of college; recollections about the people in the revolutionary movement who left a profound impression upon her; comments about a Soviet historian who reviewed Bert's Ideology in Power; Ella and her years at Hunter College--literature and history; Rose Pastor Stokes, a Communist Party USA member in the 1920s; Ella comments on those who broke with the party and why; Ella and her friend, Father Rob. Ernst; impressions of Don Frederico De Onís; reflections on "betrayal," particularly about Svetlana Stalin.
    - 198[2] December 1, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003367
      Topics: Remembering Svetlana Stalin; Leon Heikis--Soviet embassy staff person-friend; H. Lal Gupta (U. of Mexico), close friend; I. Silone (after 1945); A. Koestler (1960s) and wife, Mamaine; views on American understanding of Soviet Union in [Wolfe's] lifetime; reflections on generational differences now and in the past, e.g. parental values, education, etc.
      Ella speaks about several friends of hers. First, she speaks about Svetlana Stalin and how Svetlana was concerned with how history was recording her father. Wolfe singles out Robert Tucker as one person getting the Stalin story wrong. Ella claims Svetlana thought Bertram could properly write the history of her father, which leads to a discussion on how the Wolfes came to know Svetlana. Following the conversation about history, the interview moves to Svetlana's personal life details--about moving to England, possible position at the Hoover Institution, etc. The other subjects are Leon Heikis, of the Soviet Embassy, and H. Lal Gupta, of the University of Mexico, I. Silone (after 1945), and Arthur and Mamaine Koestler in the 1960s.
      In a second session, Wolfe and Myers discuss how Americans understand the Soviet Union. Ella argues one cannot look at Americans as just one large mass. She says scholars are better informed than "so called liberals" (her words), with the latter being misinformed. However, she notes how many of them change their mind once they visit the Soviet Union. Ella believes the biggest mass of Americans have never had to depend on the Soviet Union for trade reasons and therefore do not care about the Soviet Union and are ignorant of situations. She argues the student activists within this last group are therefore susceptible to making propaganda for the Soviet Union by proxy without knowing it; she uses the example of the anti-nuclear movement.
      The third session concentrates on generational differences. First Ella describes attitudes about education. Second, she criticizes television. Then, the Vietnam War and American foreign policy. Wolfe sees her view of generational decline as sad, not cynical.
    - 1983 January, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003370
      Topics: Rand School of Social Science, New York, 1930s--Ed Wilson (Edmund); salons in New York, 1930s, 1940s--Katherine A. Porter; Cape Cod milieu--Dos Passos, Mary Heaton Vorse; Freda Utley (1930s-1950s).
      The first conversation on the tape concerns figures in New York. Ella begins describing Edmund Wilson, focusing on his character and private life, though she does talk about his writing. Moving on, she talks about the Rand School of Social Sciences. This leads to her thoughts on many different communists/exiles from Russia. Among these is Nicolaevsky. She also discusses salons in New York in the 1930s and 1940s and Katherine A. Porter. After she speaks about the Cape Cod milieu, Dos Passos, and Mary Heaton Vorse, the tape concludes with Wolfe speaking for a few minutes about Freda Utley, including how she became pro-Hilter.
    - 1983 January 20-February 5, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003371
      Topics: Freda Utley (continued from tape 7); Dwight MacDonald, Nancy, and Gloria (his wives); Joan Colebrook and her two children; Theodore Draper, his two wives; Whittaker Chambers; Philip Jaffe and the Amerasia papers; Agnes Smedley; Anna Louise Strong; George Katkov (wrote on Kerensky, at Oxford); Max Shachtman, New York Trotskyite leader; Boris Souvarine; Joaquin Maurin.
      Picking up where the previous tape left off, Wolfe speaks about Freda Utley. She first speaks about a suicide. She then speaks about aspects of Utley's personal life, including her family, housekeeping, drinking, and hearing. The next conversation concerns a variety of people. First is Dwight MacDonald and his wives, Nancy and Gloria, and children. Wolfe speaks about the marriages and prefers Nancy to Gloria. Speaking on his professional career, she mentions he was involved in the movements of 1960s and had writer's block for a while. Next, Wolfe speaks about Joan Colebrook, concentrating on her personal life before discussing her book, her move to Australia, and their common friends. However, Wolfe does not want Colebrook to write anything about Wolfe. Wolfe discusses Theodore Draper and his two wives.
      The third conversation concerns the time after Bertram's expulsion from Mexico. Included in this is time spent discussing Whittaker Chambers, others in the Communist Party, and how he became disillusioned with the party. Wolfe says Chambers tried to get Alger Hiss to stop his activities. Wolfe says it was widely known Hiss was involved in "dirty" (her word) works. They discuss Hiss's guilt. The fourth conversation is a discussion of Philip Jaffe, the Amerasia papers, a raid of his office, and the following arrest. She says legal processes were delayed because America did not want to offend Russia as both countries were in the process of setting up the United Nations at the time. This segues into a discussion of Agnes Smedley; Wolfe comments about her for a few minutes. Next, Myers asks about Anna Louise Strong. While Wolfe did not know her, she relates information about her as Bertram had contact with Strong. Wolfe calls her "a really big fool."
      The fifth conversation begins with Wolfe commenting on the struggle of good and evil. In this light, she speaks about George Katkov and Doctor Zhivago. The sixth conversation is about New York Trotskite leader Max Shachtman. She mentions Shachtman's attacks on Bertram's book for an entire year. Years after the party purges, when they reconnected at a conference at Stanford, Wolfe found a completely different person. The last conversation concerns Boris Souvarine and Joaquin Maurin.
    - circa 1983, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003372
      Topics: Women of Latin America (matriarchal society), some reflections on contemporary American society, remembering Louis Fischer and wife, Max Eastman and his wives, Stalin's power and the extent of his control, George Lichtheim, Richard Lowenthal, Joseph Freeman.
    - 1983, 1.0 sound tape reel
      Use copy reference number: 77029_a_0003347
      Topics: Ella's perceptions of America's future, her advice to young woman today in the light of her life experiences, her long-term relationship with the Hoover Institution, major sources of disagreements between Bert and Ella, and how Ella and Bert handled different friendships outside their marriage.
      The conversation begins with Ella discussing money matters. She says that Bertram was usually generous with money, and when he was stingy, she would remind him of their lean years and how that should influence his thinking. Myers asks her to reflect on how they managed to have a successful marriage. She credits an admiration for Bertram as a mind, that there was always an intellectually-stimulating conversation to have, and a tolerance for each others' eccentricities.
      Third, Myers asks about the couple's friends, and if they caused any problems. She says that the two did not had separate friends, that they were very choosy about their friends. Of those, she says they chose friends that had common beliefs with them. This leads her to talking about Ted Switz, a chemist and agent of the Soviet secret police, and the party purges. Fourth, Myers next asks Ella for her advice to women in light of women's liberation and how to integrate all aspects of life, such as career, family, love, marriage, et cetera. Ella says she is old-fashioned, and she believes the women's liberation movement has brought about negative changes to society, citing increasing divorce rates, single parent homes, and general unhappiness. She argues women are currently reassessing the women's liberation movement and "the pendulum will eventually swing the other way." She says the changes will impact not just the individual men and women, but their children as well.
      Fifth, on the state of affairs, Wolfe argues "the pursuit of excellence has sunk very low." She is appalled at questions like "what for?" and statements such as "I don't care." Finally, Wolfe reflects on her association with the Hoover Institution. She first came to the institution in 1949-50 when Harold Fisher was Director. She says she was impressed by both the collections as well as the scholarship. She is critical of the institution's handling of Bertram's library of books but follows this by saying the help and cooperation given by the Hoover library and archives is higher than similar organizations throughout the world. She hopes Hoover will rediscover the importance of the meeting of minds.
- Videorecordings, 1986-1990, undated
  - Interview with Ella Wolfe by Rob Ernst, 1986 July
  - Frida Kahlo: A Ribbon Around a Bomb, 1990
    Use copy reference number: 77029_v_0008540
    Documentary about Frida Kahlo produced by Itzcuintli Films. Produced by Jeff Hurst, Cora Cardona, Ken Mandel; directed by Ken Mandel; cinematography by Jeff Hurst; original music by John Bryant, Frank Hames.
  - "Frida Kahlo: Portrait of an Artist," PBS, KQED San Francisco, 1988